Guide to the Kellogg Family Papers 1755-1890 MS 016 MS 016 MS 016
Cornwall Historical Society
Kellogg Family Papers
1755-1890
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 016
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains items related to four generations of the Kellogg family of Cornwall.
Provenance
unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"The Kelloggs were prominent figures in Cornwall’s legal, ecclesiastical, and military life, and intermarried with many other of Cornwall’s leading families. In 1774, Judah Kellogg (1739-1819) moved to Cornwall from Stratford, Connecticut with his wife, Mary Tomlinson Kellogg (1744-1836). Judah Kellogg served as a deacon in the First Church, and as a justice of the peace after 1779. He also represented Cornwall at the state assembly for four years during the American Revolution, from 1776-1779. Judah Kellogg died in Cornwall on April 20, 1819.William Kellogg (1769-1829) was born in Stratford and moved to Cornwall as a young child. William was Judah and Mary’s eldest son, and succeeded his father as town clerk. William married Dennis, a daughter of Heman Swift, and had four sons. He died in Cornwall on May 28, 1829.Frederick Kellogg (1801-1891) was born to William and Dennis Kellogg in Cornwall on September 5, 1801. Frederick was a storeowner and, like his father and grandfather, active in local legal and political matters. On September 16, 1829, he married Ruth Calhoun (1805-1869), daughter of Dr. John Calhoun. Frederick represented Cornwall for four years in the state legislature, and was appointed a judge in 1852. In the early 1840s, he played a key role in getting the Housatonic Railroad constructed. He died in Cornwall on August 14, 1891.Frederick’s older brother Philo Kellogg (1794-1862) was born in Cornwall on March 1, 1794. Like his brother, he also served as a representative and as a judge. He was married to Charlotte Miles and lived on his grandfather Judah’s old farm. He died in Cornwall in 1862.Theodore Kellogg (1824-1903) was born to Philo and Charlotte Kellogg in 1824. Theodore also entered the legal profession and worked as an attorney before being disbarred for “intemperance.” He was well known for his eccentric nature and humor, and was married to Maria C. Sturges (1831-1904)."
Scope and Content Note
The collection is contained in three archival boxes. The first box of the series contains items relating to specific members of the Kellogg family. Items are organized generationally into sections, and filed chronologically within those sections.
Series II contains general records that are not attributed to any specific member of the Kellogg family. Documents are divided into sections devoted to ecclesiastical, legal, military, property, library, and miscellaneous records, respectively. Within each section, items are organized in chronological order.
Series III is comprised of papers related to families associated with the Kelloggs. It is specifically divided into sections for the Calhoun, Pierce, and Stone families. Items within those sections are filed in chronological order.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Kellogg Family Papers
Calhoun, Pierce, and Stone Family Papers
Miscellanea
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Correspondence; Articles; Deeds; records; Cornwall Historical Society; Cornwall Historical Society; Sturges, Maria C (1831-1904); Kellogg, Philo (1794-1862); Kellogg, Theodore (1824-1903); Kellogg, William (1769-1829); Calhoun, Ruth (1805-1869); Kellogg, Frederick (1801-1891); Kellogg, Mary Tomlinson (1744-1836); Kellogg, Judah (1739-1819)
- Kellogg Family
  - Judah Kellogg
    - Account book, 1769-1774 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Complaint by Solomon Emmons against thieves who stole his watermelon crop, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - School account, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Ezra Stiles, regarding Stiles’ farm, 1781-1787 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    - Correspondence with H. Silliman, regarding monetary issue with E. Stiles, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Summons for Patrick Hindman, for debt issue, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Writ of Edmund Beach vs. S. Bassett, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Complaint of Thankful Butler against W. Crammar, for impregnating her out of wedlock, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Complaint of Daniel Abbott against James Dean and Ebenezer Dickinson, for Sabbath-breaking, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Complaint of Abel Sharp against John Holcomb, for profanity, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Order to county sheriff to arrest Samuel Bassett, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Complaint of Ozias Hurlburt against Joseph Wilcox, William Andrews, and Henry Sedgwick, for drunkenness, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Complaint of Solomon Emmons against Stephen North, for breaking the peace, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Certificate of abatement for indigent residents of Cornwall, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Attachment in case of Adna Allen vs. Elijah Allen, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Copy of complaint for neglect of working on the highways, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Complaint of Bradley Catlin against Henry Sedgwick, for swearing, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Deed of J. Swift to Samuel Canfield, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Journal and remarks, 1805-1806 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - “Memorandum,” with historical notes on back, 1809-1810 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - William Kellogg
    - Correspondence with John Jeffers, regarding the Northwest Indian War, 1787-1794 (Box 1, Folder 25-29)
    - Military discharge, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Complaint against Elisha Hurlburt, Jr., for swearing, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Receipt of proprietors’ treasurer, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Appointment as tax collector, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - The Balance, newspaper, with note to editor, 1802-1805 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Warrant for state tax, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Order with Silas Patterson and Edmund Harrison, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence regarding mail route from New Haven to Cornwall, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Letter from Timothy Rogers, regarding Revolutionary War pension, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Agreement of William Clark and Mrs. G.W. Perkins, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Copy of petition to state legislature for railroad, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - List of town accounts, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Frederick Kellogg
    - Deed from Rufus Payne to Daniel M. Brinsmade, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Form of attestation, regarding possession of Heman Swift’s rolls and records, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Account book, 1849-1854 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Deed from John C. Lewis, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Receipt of Grace Clark, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Copy of charter and survey of the town of Cornwall, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Law office notebook, 1874-1908 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Library trustee’s report, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Philo Kellogg
    - Note with committee to raise funds for extending Housatonic Railroad to Cornwall, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Bond with Lewis Catlin, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Theodore Kellogg
    - Proclamation after being elected Hay Ward, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Letter sent to J.A. Wilson, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Calhoun, Pierce and Stone Families
  - Calhoun Family Documents
    - Letter from Boston Committee of Donations, thanking Cornwall donors, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bill of Peter Sherman against Esq. Calhoun, 1789 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Vital records of the Fay family of Bennington, Vermont, 1792 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Note of Joseph Calhoun, regarding property of Solomon Palmer, 1803 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence of John Calhoun, regarding war records of Heman Swift, 1830 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Calhoun vital records, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence between Dr. John Calhoun and Wm. Kellogg, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Prescription by Dr. John Calhoun, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Writing attributed to Dr. John Calhoun, about medical items, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pierce Family Documents
    - John Pierce Deeds, 1756-1810 (Box 3, Folder 11-32)
    - Maps and surveys of Pierce Estate, 1750-1797 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Power of attorney, John Pierce for Benjamin Parris, 1769 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Memoranda of “Long John” Pierce, 1793 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Suit of Clemens Dibble against John Pierce, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Estate minutes, 1822-1827 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Seth Pierce request for power of attorney from heirs of John Pierce to reclaim land, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Stone Family Documents
    - Marriage certificate of J.B. Chaffer and Hannah Birdsey, officiated by Rev. Timothy Stone, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Marriage certificate of John Lovell and Catherine Gold, officiated by Rev. Timothy Stone, 1825 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Lease from John Pierce Stone to his parents, Timothy and Mary Stone, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Will of Timothy and Mary Stone, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Mary Stone memoranda regarding inheritance, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Lease from John Pierce Stone to his parents, Timothy and Mary Stone, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Conditions of Mary Stone giving her house to John Pierce Stone, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Will of Mary Stone, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Memoranda respecting Mary Stone’s portion of unspecified estate, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Deed from Seth Pierce, et al., to Sally Merwin and John P. Stone, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Sally Merwin’s will, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Inventory of Sally Merwin estate, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Division of Sally Merwin’s property, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - John Pierce Stone deeds, 1832-1866 (Box 3, Folder 52-57)
    - Note of John P. Stone to Timothy D.P. Stone, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Obligation of John P. Stone to pay parents and sister, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence between Timothy D.P. Stone and John P. Stone, 1856-1862 (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
    - Items relating to the estate of Ezekiel Birdseye, 1861-1863 (Box 3, Folder 62-65)
    - Unsigned letter written to “brother", undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
- Miscellanea
  - Ecclesiastical Records
    - Petition of parishioners of southwest Cornwall to be set off to Kent congregation, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Petition for the removal of Reverend Hezekiah Gold, 1783 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Second Ecclesiastical Society rate bill list, 1795 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - North Cornwall church petition to be legally made into a local ecclesiastical society, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lists of residents living in first and second ecclesiastical societies, 1802, , undated (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
    - Preamble and subscriptions to fund the First Church, 1802-1804 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Circular letter regarding the funding of missions, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letter from E.W. Andrews, declining to preach at First Church dedication, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Articles of faith, declaration, and covenant of the North Cornwall Church, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Debt Lawsuits
    - Matthew Patterson v. Samuel Wickwire, 1784 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - John Pierce v. Elijah Allen, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ozias Blake v. Ananias Derthick, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Lyman Fox v. Peter Richards, 1820 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Abel Judson v. Julius Jackson, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - James Blake v. Abijah Painter, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Heman Bierce v. Nathan S. Marchant, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Obadiah Bierce v. Joshua Birdsill, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Isaac A. Norton v. Henry Richardson, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - E. Barber v. Ananias Derthick, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Obadiah Bierce v. Joshua Birdsill, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Samuel Seelye v. Abbin Cross, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lemuel Mentin v. George Muster, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Gideon Pangman v. Roswell Willson, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Samuel Seelye v. Abbit Northrop, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Harvey Kellogg v. Nathan Hart, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Uriah Wiston v. Nial Grannis, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Legal Documents
    - Samuel Bartholimis v. Stephen North, for assault, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Charles C. Beers v. John Cross, for assault, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Ebenezer Birdseye v. Henry Reed, for trespassing, 1824; , undated (Box 2, Folder 38-41)
    - Joel Bunnel v. Job, Smith, Nathan, and Benedict Beach, for trespassing and killing his hog, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 42-44)
    - Asa Emmons v. Joel Wright, for trespassing, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - State of Conn. v. Samuel Kingsman, for Sabbath-breaking, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - State of Conn. v. Robert Carter, for drunkenness, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Complaint against William Kellogg, Rufus Payne, Elijah Steele, and Charles E. Jackson, for playing cards, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - A v. B., “Declaration for an unsound Negro", undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Distribution of Lt. Ebenezer Dibble’s estate, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Note of Joel Moss to Zachariah H. Jones, 1785 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Freehold note of Solomon Palmer, endorsed by Timothy Rose, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Military Items
    - Amos Johnson application for expenses paid while a prisoner of war, 1778 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Request sent by the state to selectmen for the return of public military stores, 1787 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Jacob Scovel application for Revolutionary War pension, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Documents related to Corporal Nelson Clark’s discharge, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 57-58)
    - Inspection returns for soldiers from the 9th Regiment, 4th Brigade, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Property Records
    - Division of Samuel Thomas Gruman property, 1753 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Deed from committee of the Connecticut Colony to Zachariah Tomlinson, for Cornwall lands, 1755 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Lease from Matthew Keeler to John Dibble, 1770 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Letter sent to John Pierce from Matthew Keeler, regarding property issue, 1783 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Letter from Yale College, regarding Cornwall property, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Report of commissioners on proposed turnpike in Kent, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Lease from Benjamin Gold to Stephen Gold, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Inquiry about clay bed from H.M. Hart to S.C. Beers, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Copy of pp. 30-31 of proprietor’s records, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Votes of proprietors, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Property map, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Library Records
    - Votes regarding operation, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Request for meeting to sell books, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Warning for proprietor’s meeting, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Accounts, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - ‘Catalogue of the Publick Library", undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Portion of constitution and original members list, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Printed materials
    - “An Acrostic on Benedict Arnold,” by Anonymous, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Booklet, “Mr. Daggett’s Argument Before the General Assembly of the State of Connecticut", 1804 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Nomination for assistants, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Invitation to join resurrected Connecticut Society of the Cincinnati, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 80)